PANDE PUTU ERAWIJANTARI

Biological Information-PhD candidate | Gut Microbiome Researcher



CONTACT

PORTFOLIO

+81 3-5734-3591 / +81 70-4024-7949 : Phone

erawijantari.p.aa@m.titech.ac.jp: F-mail

1528550, Tokyo, Meguro-ku, Ookayama 2-12-1, M6-3: Address

: linkedin.com/in/erawijantari-pande-putu Linkedin

Researchgate: researchgate.net/profile/Erawijantari Pande Putu

: https://twitter.com/erawijantaript

SUMMARY

As a PhD candidate in Biological Information, I have incorporated skills in biology and bioinformatics. Originally trained in biology, I have worked on the deep-sea metagenomics study, synthetic biology and phytochemical effectiveness as anticancer. Afterward, I started to study deeply on bioinformatics with the help of the enormous data and computational tools that currently available publicly. My current research mainly focuses on the dynamics of human gut microbiome in the gastrointestinal-related diseases. This study uses the multi-omics approach which involves the metagenomics and metabolomics analyses on human fecal samples. In the future, I hope my contribution can help to understand the microbiome as effects or consequences in gastrointestinal related diseases and treatment effectiveness. Outside research, I like to spend my spare time on reading, watching, or traveling. To keep myself motivated, I like to constantly challenge myself, do the positive self-talk and self-tracking by journaling which can sharpen my focus on achieving the goals I set.

EDUCATION

PhD CANDIDATE 2017-Present TOKYO INSTITUTE OF TECHNOLOGY - JAPAN

Major in biological information at the School of Life Science and Technology.

Focus of research is in gut microbiome dynamics in gastrointestinal-related diseases

Supervised by Associate Professor Takuji Yamada

MASTER

TOKYO INSTITUTE OF TECHNOLOGY - JAPAN

OF SCIENCE Major in biological information at the School of Life Science and Technology. 2015-2017

Master thesis focused on the effect of gastrectomy as gastric cancer treatment on human gut

microbiome.

BACHELOR OF SCIENCE INSTITUTE TEKNOLOGI BANDUNG (BANDUNG INSTITUTE OF TECHNOLOGY) - INDONESIA

Major in biology at the School of Life Science and Technology.

Bachelor thesis focused on the mutation and expression of beta glucosidase gene isolated from the 2010-2014

Kawio Island, Sangihe Talaud, North Sulawesi, Indonesia deep sea metagenome.

RESEARCH

HFRFDITARY COLORECTAL **CANCER** 2018-Present

GUT MICROBIOME PROFILE OF PATIENTS WITH HEREDITARY COLORECTAL CANCER

Numerous studies have indicated that gut microbiome plays important roles in development of colorectal cancer. The link between the gut microbiome with the hereditary form of colorectal cancer is yet to be discovered. Understanding the roles of microbiome in the hereditary colorectal cancer can help to decipher the 'nature' vs 'nurture' problem in microbiome study, especially related to colorectal cancer.

GUT MICROBIOME 2017-Present GASTROINTESTINAL BARIER ALTERATION EFFECT ON HUMAN GUT MICROBIOME

Alterations of gastrointestinal structure caused by surgery or other medical operations may affect the human gut microbiome conditions. Understanding this alteration effect can provide a better understanding on the effectiveness of the medical treatment to the patients' outcome based on the gut

microbiome point of view.

GASTRECTOMY GUT MICROBIOME 2015-Present THE EFFECT OF GASTRECTOMY AS GASTRIC CANCER TREATMENT ON HUMAN GUT

MICROBIOME

Several researches have been carried out to observe the effect of gastrectomy for morbid obesity. However its effect as gastric cancer treatment still remains unknown. In order to analyze the effect, this study was performed for comprehensive characterization of human gut microbiome in the fecal sample from the gastrectomy patients with the history of gastric cancer.

PHYTOCHEMICAL ANTI CANCER 2014-2015 PHYTOCHEMICAL COMPOUND ANALYSIS AS ANTICANCER ON THE CELL LINE MODEL

Phytochemical compound is a candidate for cancer medicines. In addition, In vitro human cell line models have been widely used for cancer pharmacogenomics studies as well as in the screening of anticancer candidate from phytochemical compound. This study aimed to provide a better understanding on the mechanism of phytochemical compound as the cancer treatment based on the cell line model. Several results of this study have already been published.

SYNTHETIC BIOLOGY 2013-2014 WHOLE CELL BIOCATALYST FOR PET PLASTIC DEGRADATION

This research used synthetic biology approach to design an *Escherichia coli* that could degrade the polyethylene terephthalate (PET) plastics. This project has won gold medal at the International Genetically Engineered Machine (iGEM) Giant Jambore 2014.

WORK EXPERIENCES

STUDENT INTERN-DATA ANALYST 2018-Present METABOLOGENOMICS, INC.

Contribute as data analyst related to gut microbiome related diseases and treatment effectiveness. This company has focus on developing technology for stratified health care based on personalized gut microbiome.

RESEARCH ASSISTANT 2017-Present

YAMADA LABORATORY, SCHOOL OF LIFE SCIENCE AND TECHNOLOGY, TOKYO INSTITUTE OF TECHNOLOGY

Conduct primary and secondary source research as Research Assistant to Associate Professor Takuji Yamada. Contribute to methods development for the eukaryotic fraction detection and metagenomics analysis pipeline.

RESEARCH SCIENTIST 2014-2015

BIOMOLECULAR AND BIOMEDICAL RESEARCH CENTER, ARETHA MEDIKA UTAMA, BANDUNG, WEST JAVA. INDONESIA

Carried out analyses on the phytochemical bioactive screening and the potential of Mesenchymal Stem Cells for cancer treatment using human cells line model.

ON JOB TRAINING 2013 ENVIRONMENTAL AFFAIRS DEPARTMENT, PT NEWMONT NUSA TENGGARA, SUMBAWA, WEST NUSA TENGGARA, INDONESIA

Participated in the environmental assessment as the results of mining process and propose the solutions based on the analysis.

PUBLICATIONS

Widowati W, Darsono L, Suherman J, Fauziah N, Maesaroh M, **Erawijantari PP**. Anti-inflammatory effect of mangosteen (*Garcinia mangostana* L.) peel extract and its compounds in LPS-induced RAW264.7 cell. Nat Prod Sci. 2016 Sep;22(3):147-153.

Widowati W, Wijaya L, Laksmitawati DR, Widyanto RM, **Erawijantari PP**, Fauziah N, Bachtiar I, Sandra F. Tea flavonoids induced differentiation of peripheral blood-derived mononuclear cells into peripheral blood-derived endothelial progenitor cells and suppressed intracellular reactive oxygen species level of peripheral blood-derived endothelial progenitor cells. Nat Prod Sci. 2016 Jun;22(2):87-92.

Nurhayati B, Wibowo MS, Widyastuti Y, **Erawijantari PP**, Widowati W, Pratama MRF, Kartawinata TG. In silico Analysis of Plantaricin EF that Expressed by Plasmid-Associated Bacteriocin Production Gene of Lactobacillus plantarum IBL-2 for Anti-Candida Agent Potential. Res J Microbiol. 2015 Dec;10(12):582-591.

Kartika D, Widyanto B, **Erawijantari PP**, Widowati W. In vitro study of Myristica fragrans seed (Nutmeg) ethanolic extract and quercetin compound as anti-inflammatory agent. International Journal of Research in Medical Sciences. 2015 Sept; 3(9): 2303-2310.

CONFERENCE PRESENTATIONS

2015

2018

2018

2015

2018

Erawijantari PP, Mizutani S, Shiroma H, Yachida S, Yamada T.Metagenomic and metabolomic profiling to characterize the effect of gastrectomy as gastric cancer treatment on human gut microbiome. June 26-28, 2018; 7th International Human Microbiome Consortium: Translating microbiome science.

Erawijantari PP, Mizutani S, Shiroma H, Yachida S, Yamada T. Characterization of human gut microbiome and metabolome of gastric cancer patients after gastrectomy. March 5, 2018; *Keystone Symposia on Molecular and Cellular Biology: Manipulation of the Gut Microbiota for Metabolic Health.*

Erawijantari PP, Moeis MR. Mutation and expression of β-glucosidase gene isolated from Kawio island, North Sulawesi Deep Sea, Metagenome. Nov 3, 2014; *5th International Conference on Mathematics and Natural Science*.

ACHIEVEMENTS

International Human Microbiome Consortium 2018-Early Career Scientist Bursary recipient.

2017 Japanese Government (Monbukagakusho:MEXT) Scholarship recipient for PhD Student.

2015 Japanese Government (Monbukagakusho:MEXT) Scholarship recipient for Master Student.

2014 Gold medalist as ITB_Indonesia team on iGEM (International Genetically Engineered Machine)

EXPERTISE

Bioinformatics
Data analysis and Statistic
Biology molecular
Python Programing
R Programing
Linux

REFERENCES

TAKUJI YAMADA, ASSOCIATE PROFESOR School of Life Science and Technology Tokyo Institute of Technology, Tokyo, Japan +813-5734-3629, takuji@bio.titech.ac.jp

LANGUAGE

INDONESIA ENGLISH JAPANESE : native proficiency

: professional working proficiency

: elementary proficiency